HOWL'S MOVING CASTLE
For my sisters. Happy birthday, 2026!
Translation by Colin W
Sophie?
I've closed the shop.
Why aren't you coming to the party with us?
I'm going to finish this up instead.
Go have fun.
Alright, see you tomorrow.
Okay, ladies!
Ahh, just a sec!
How does this look on me?
Look, Howl's castle!
What, where?
Look how close it is!
My, my...
Do you think he's in town?
He's gone...
He's just hiding in the clouds
what with all those army planes flying about.
Did you hear about Martha from the south end?
They say Howl stole her heart!
Don't freak me out...
Don't worry, he'll never come after you.
Hurry it up!
Hey little lady, looking for something?
Oh, no, I'm just fine.
Then how about a quick drink with us?
Come on, what do you say?
I'm sorry, I can't... I have somewhere to be.
Hey, she's a cute one.
How old are you? You live around here?
Please let me pass!
You've scared her off with that beard of yours.
She's even cute when she's angry.
Ah, here you are!
Finally found you.
Who the hell are you?
She's with me.
Why don't you guys for a little stroll?
Forgive them, they're not bad people.
Where are you headed?
Why don't I see you there safely.
I'm just going to Chezarya...
Act normal. I'm being followed.
Come.
Sorry, looks like I've gotten you involved.
This way!
Up we go!
Stretch out your legs and walk like normal.
That's right, don't be afraid.
You're good at this!
I'll draw them off.
Wait here for a bit before you head down.
Okay.
That's my girl.
Here you go.
Is there a chocolate with your name on it?
Hey, gimme one of those too!
My sister?
Lettie, hurry back! We're waiting!
Sophie!
Lettie.
What's wrong?
They said you just dropped from the sky!
When did you become an angel?
I feel like I'm dreaming.
Here Lettie, use the office.
Ah, thanks, but I need to get back right away.
He must have been a wizard!
He was the nicest person I've ever met.
He saved me, actually.
Wait, are you sure
he didn't steal your heart like the others?
Just be glad that wasn't Howl
or you'd be eaten up by now!
Don't worry.
Howl only goes after the pretty ones.
Oh come on...
Listen, the world is a dark place these days!
They're even saying the Witch of the Wastes is wandering about.
Are you listening?
Geez...
Lettie, Madeleine just finished up.
I'll be out in a sec!
Sure.
I'll get going.
I feel much better now that I've seen you.
Hey, Lettie!
Good to see you!
Okay, listen.
Are you really going to stay cooped up in that hat shop
for the rest of your life?
It's all we have left of Father
and I am the eldest, so...
No!
I'm asking if you really want to be a hatter!
Well...
Lettie, see you later!
Come around to the shop next time!
I'm going.
Sophie
you have to decide your future for yourself!
I know.
I'm sorry, we're closed.
Forgive me
I thought I had locked the door.
Cheap hats in a cheap little shop.
You're nothing much to look at either.
We are but a humble hatter.
Please be on your way.
You're going to tell the Witch of the Wastes what to do?
You're brave.
The Witch of the Wastes?
I've cursed you, but don't bother trying to tell anyone about it.
Say hi to Howl for me.
Is that really me? Oh my, oh my...
Gotta calm down...
Panicking won't solve anything, Sophie...
This is nothing, it's nothing...
Calm down, calm down...
I'm home!
Madam, welcome back!
What do you think?
It's all the rage in Kingsbury.
It looks amazing.
Wait 'til they all get a look at me.
Madam
Sophie hasn't come down yet this morning.
I wonder what could be the matter?
Don't come in, I have a wicked cold!
I don't want you to catch it.
My Lord, you sound 90 years old.
I'm just going to stay in bed today.
Really? Okay... see you later.
Listen Granny, you're going to be just fine.
You seem healthy enough
and these clothes even fit you better now.
But I can't stay here, can I.
Oww... getting old isn't easy, is it.
Shall I help you down, ma'am?
How kind of you young man, I'll be fine.
I mean, sure.
But where are you going anyway?
Just past where you're going.
I'm telling you, lady!
It's just wizards and their lot up ahead!
I'll keep that in mind!
She's heading into the valley at this hour?
Yeah, says her sister lives out there.
I haven't even made it that far.
At least my teeth are still as they were.
You know what? I need a cane.
Up we go!
Oww...
Might be a bit thick.
What a stubborn stick.
I might be old but I'm no pushover!
Come on!
A scarecrow?
For a moment I thought it was another witch's trick.
Wait a minute... how are you standing on your own?
You've got a turnip for a head.
You know, I never liked turnips...
Well, I'm sure you're glad to be out of that bush.
Farewell!
It's getting colder.
The town still seems so close.
Hey, don't follow me!
You don't need to return the favour.
You're some sort of magic thing too, right?
I've had quite enough of magic and witches, thank you!
Go prop yourself up somewhere nice.
What a perfect little cane. Thank you.
While you're at it
I sure wouldn't mind if you found me a place for the night.
Looks like I got more clever with age too.
Look at that thing.
I never thought that age meant
my body would stop doing what I tell it.
I smell smoke.
Is there a hut nearby?
Mr. Turnip, this is Howl's castle!
I told you to find me a place for the night, but...
I never thought...
How is this even a castle?
Is that the way in?
Hey, slow down!
Come on...
Are you letting me on or not?
My shawl...
Turnip, I'm heading in. It looks warm in there.
I don't think he'll mind a guest.
Thanks again!
Even if it is Howl, he'll never eat
an old hag like me!
It's farewell for real this time.
A turnip you may be, but I like you.
All the best!
What is this place?
It's practically falling apart.
Well, I suppose at this age
there's not much that can surprise me anymore.
That's quite the curse eh.
It's going to be a pain to get rid of that one.
The fire is talking to me.
Seems you can't even talk about it either.
Are you Howl?
Nope, I'm Calcifer
the terrible Fire Demon!
Okay Calcifer
can you get rid of this curse on me?
Sure!
All you gotta do
is get rid of the magic binding me here
and I'll undo yours as well.
A deal with the devil?
Can I really trust you?
Probably not, I am a demon after all.
So much for that.
No really, I'm a victim here!
Howl bound me in a contract
and he works me like a dog in this place!
I'm the one moving this castle, did you know that?
Oh, that must be tough...
If you can figure out the nature of our contract
then the spells binding me will unwind.
Then I'll fix you too, okay?
Alright... it's a deal...
Lady.
Hey, lady!
How am I going to explain this to him...
Huh? Who's this?
Port Town!
How did she even get in here?
I come!
Ah, the honourable Mayor.
It's well past morning, sir.
Is Lord Jenkins at home?
My master is out.
I shall speak in his stead.
This is a summons from his Majesty the King.
It's war.
By royal decree, all wizards, fortune tellers,
and even witches are to answer the call.
See that you and your master report in for briefing.
Who even wants a war anyway?
And who might you be?
Calcifer let me in.
I did not!
She left herself in from the wastes last night!
The wastes?
That's odd.
You're not a witch, are you?
You think a witch could get in here?
It's Port Town again!
A customer maybe?
I come!
What is it, child?
My mom sent me over.
Ah, the usual charm?
Yeah.
Wait here while I fetch it.
What?
I'm not in the wastes.
Excuse me, are you a witch?
Oh yeah! The scariest one in the whole kingdom.
Cast this powder to the wind and the ships will have smooth sailing.
Until next time.
Stop playing tricks on my customers!
And you should stop with that silly costume.
This isn't a costume, it's magic!
It's Kingsbury this time!
I come!
Is this the residence of Sir Pendragon?
It is.
I come bearing an official summons from the King.
Please tell him that he is to appear
at the palace at once.
I will relay the message.
A city fit for a king!
Get back in here or I'm locking you out.
Just stay out of the way!
I said cut it out! I'm going to get angry!
This is a magic house, isn't it?
Lady...
Where does the black one lead to?
Only Howl knows that.
I'm going to make breakfast.
You even got some bacon and eggs sitting here!
Yeah, but without Howl
we can't use the fire.
Don't be silly, I'll do it.
You can't!
Calcifer only listens
to what Howl tells him.
Yeah! I'm not cooking no eggs!
How did my hat get on the floor...
Alright Calcifer, time for work.
No way! I'm a demon!
You can't make me do anything!
Oh? Maybe a little water will improve your motivation?
Or maybe I'll just tell Howl
about our little deal?
I never should have let you in here!
So, are you helping me or not?
See, that wasn't so hard.
Just watch! I'll burn your stupid bacon!
He's doing what she says...?
I could use a cup of tea...
Is there a kettle around here?
Welcome back, sir.
There are letters from the kings
for both Jenkins and Pendragon.
Calcifer
look at you doing what you're told.
She blackmailed me!
That's not something just anybody could do.
Who are you?
Me? I'm old Sophie
your new cleaner!
Here, let me do it.
Pass me two more bacon strips and six eggs.
Nice.
Oh that's good.
So good!
Who exactly hired you as cleaner?
I hired myself.
I've never seen such a dump.
Markl, get the plates!
You're all picking on me!
You too, Ms. Sophie.
You can sit here.
Take one.
These are the only ones that aren't dirty.
I've got my work cut out for me.
Thanks!
Oh, thank you.
Everyone, bon appétit.
Bon appétit!
It's really been a while
since we had a proper breakfast like this.
Looks like I'm teaching manners too...
So, what's that in your pocket?
Where did this come from?
Give it here.
It burnt the table! What is it, Howl?
Old magic, and powerful.
Is it from the Witch of the Wastes?
"Loveless one, he who swallowed a star"
"your heart belongs to me."
So much for the table.
It's gone! Amazing.
The burn might be gone but the curse remains.
Please finish your meals.
Move the castle about a hundred kilometers.
Delicious...
And send some hot water up to the bath.
What? Already?
Are you a servant of the Witch of the Wastes or something?
Don't be ridiculous!
After what that hag did to...
I'm actually... I...
I've had it!
That Witch better watch out.
The next time I see her, she's in big trouble!
Come on, we have work to do.
Alright you bugs!
Better run now before I sweep you out the door!
I bet you were having a great time before I came along...
I'd like a certain charm whipped up.
Can it wait?
A witch rages within.
Sophie, I'm going out!
I'll die without more wood!
What are you doing with those?
I'm gonna fall!
I'm going to clear out the ashes. Won't take a minute.
This is really bad.
I can't hold on!
I'm going out...
I'm seriously falling.
I can't...
Help ... can't hold on ...
Sophie, hurry!
I'd appreciate it if you'd treat my friend a little better.
Where are you going, Howl?
Markl, please tell our new cleaner
to be a bit more careful as she cleans.
What did you do?
She almost killed me!
If I die
then so does Howl!
I'm a cleaner. Cleaning's my job, so stop complaining.
No, not the second floor!
If I were you kiddo
I'd hurry and put away all the things you don't want touched, eh?
Do mine later, okay?
A little bit of anger and I feel good as new.
What a place...
Look at this!
Are you moving the castle all on your own?
What? Of course I am.
You're amazing, Calcifer!
Your magic is the best. I'm floored!
You think?
You really think so?
No, not yet!
What a view.
It's called the Stellar Lake.
There's something stuck down there.
Markl, give me a hand.
Up you go!
A scarecrow!
Ah... I named him "Turnip".
You just love getting caught in things, don't you?
Looks like he has a crush on me.
He must have followed me here.
You're really not a witch?
Oh but I am.
And this witch just can't stand a messy house!
Turnip, you're pulling too hard!
Looks like he loves laundry.
It'll dry in no time.
Do you think he's a demon or something?
Calcifer doesn't seem to mind him.
He could even be a spirit from another world.
But I still can't believe we're in such a perfect place.
Sophie, I put all the laundry away.
Thank you. I guess it's time to head back in then.
What a strange place.
I've never felt this way before.
You stink of flesh and iron.
Much more of that and you won't be able to turn back.
You see this?
Sophie put them there for me.
The war is getting worse.
It's a sea of flames from the beaches to the northern border.
I can't stand bomb fires.
They just burn whatever's in front of them, no respect.
Some of my colleagues were after me too.
The Witch of the Wastes?
No, just small fry. But they had turned themselves into monsters.
Ahh... they're going to regret that.
Probably no way back to their human forms.
Might not be so bad... they won't remember what sadness feels like.
The kings want you too, don't they?
They do, but...
Boil some water for me, will you?
What? Again?
He's been going through way too much water.
I'm telling you, he's not going to eat any.
It's fine.
Mornin'.
Good morning.
The morning market, I can't wait.
You know I've never seen the ocean?
Look at it sparkling!
Same as always...
I don't like potatoes.
Pay the man.
Thank you.
Come again!
All of it's fresh off the boats!
That's a tender one.
I don't like fish.
There's a battleship returning!
Looks like there was another battle.
Seriously? Sorry ma'am, come back later.
It's burning!
Hang in there!
Sophie, let's go get a closer look.
No, I can't stand things like this... let's go back.
And that's one of the newer models...
Markl, there's a Rubber Man over there.
Stay still! It works for the Witch of the Wastes.
It's gone.
Can the others not see it or something?
There! In the sky!
There's a bomber there!
Sophie, that's an enemy airship!
Sophie, it's dropping pamphlets.
Leave them! Do not pick those up!
Sophie, are you okay?
Get me a glass of water.
Sophie, did you mess with my drawers?
Look at this!
Look at this colour!
Oh... what nice hair.
I said look!
You messed with the drawers
and all the spells got mixed up!
I didn't mess with anything, I just put things in order.
Cleaning, cleaning... always cleaning!
I told you not to get carried away!
It's over.
I'll never recover from this.
Oh come on, you look fine.
In fact, I quite like it.
No, it's over. If I'm not beautiful
how am I supposed to go on living?
Howl, cut it out!
He's drawing out shadow spirits!
This happened once before
when a girl dumped him!
Howl, cheer up.
You can just dye your hair back, can't you?
Oh, see if I care!
I've never been beautiful, not once!
I can't stand it here!
Thank you, Turnip.
You're such a gentleman.
Sophie, come back in, quick!
Howl's in trouble!
Howl man, seriously! I'm going to go out!
Save me!
He's so dramatic.
Is he dead?
He'll be fine.
A little temper tantrum never killed anybody.
Give me a hand with him.
Fill the tub right to the top!
Come on Howl, use your feet.
Alright Markl, you take care of the rest.
Now I have to clean all this up.
I'm coming in.
I brought you some warm milk.
I'll just leave it here then.
Drink it before it cools off, okay?
Stay with me, Sophie.
Want the milk?
The Witch of the Wastes is looking for this place.
I saw her lackies down at the harbour.
Despite appearances, I'm a coward.
All these trinkets
are charms to confuse her seeking spells.
I fear her, truly.
Why is she after you in the first place?
I was actually the one who made first contact.
She fascinated me... but I came to regret it.
She was horrible.
And now, with the war
I've been summoned to the courts of both kingdoms.
As Jenkins on one side, Pendragon on the other.
How many names do you go by?
As many as I need to maintain my freedom.
Why not just turn the kings down?
Look there.
We swear an oath to the crown
upon entrance to the Academy of Wizardry.
Well, just go tell them yourself!
Just be honest with them.
"Under no circumstances will I participate"
"in this foolish war of yours!"
...you don't know what they can be like.
Well, they are kings after all.
Aren't they supposed to care for their subjects?
I've got it!
You can go for me!
You'll claim to be Pendragon's mother.
Tell them your son is a useless layabout
and they'll leave me alone!
Madam Suliman might even get off my back!
Madam Suliman?
Why the hat?
I already fixed up your clothes with magic.
See you two later.
Good luck!
A good luck charm to find your way back home.
Don't worry. I'll be following you in disguise.
Now go!
I'm not so sure about this anymore...
He's following me?
Don't tell me he turned into a crow or something...
No, Howl would go for something flashier.
...but not that.
The castle was further than I thought.
You're not Howl, are you?
Oh, honestly...
An old dog? Really?
You don't really get how hard
I have it at my age, do you?
What a pleasant surprise.
You're that hatter girl, no?
The Witch of the Wastes!
Thanks for delivering my letter.
Did he like it?
Oh, don't get me started.
At least thanks to you I've happily changed careers!
I'm so happy for you.
More importantly...
what are you doing at the castle?
Finding a job. I'm sick of that nut Howl!
And you?
I've been summoned.
That louse Suliman has finally realized
that they're doomed without my abilities.
I couldn't care less.
Just get rid of this curse you put on me!
I wish I could... I'm great at casting them
but disspelling them... not so much.
See you up there!
Come back here!
I said wait!
I could have given her a good whack with my cane
if you hadn't been slowing me down!
What's the matter with you two?
Magicks are forbidden beyond this point, ma'am!
Please ascend on foot!
Suliman, that cow.
She dares to make me take the stairs myself?
We've almost caught up.
Act natural.
Oh, come on...
Why are you so heavy?
Hey you... come back here...
Did you remember how to remove the curse?
I told you...
I can't...
Looks like you have some studying to do!
I don't believe this.
How did she get up there so quickly?
Give me a minute...
You look terrible. Why not come back tomorrow?
Fifty years. Fifty years I've been waiting in the wastes
for my triumphant return
after they kicked me out of this place.
Well, suck it up then!
I'm not in the mood to lend you a hand.
Let's go, Howl.
You heartless witch...
Just wait 'til I get my hands on you...
You're almost there!
If you'll follow me, ma'am.
Why not give that one a hand first?
I'm afraid we're forbidden from doing so.
Ridiculous.
The King invited her here, didn't he?
Just a few more steps!
Almost there!
You call yourself a witch?
Shut up already...
You're a mess...
Madam Pendragon and the Witch of the Wastes!
Look alive.
Haven't you been waiting ages for this?
Madam Pendragon and the Witch of the Wastes!
Pendragon? I know that name from somewhere...
Of course you do.
It's the name of my old hat shop.
Was it...?
This way, please.
A chair!
It's mine!
Howl, where are you going?
You're expected.
I'm told you're Howl's mother.
That's right, we go by the name Pendragon.
Forgive the stairs. Please, sit.
Thank you.
I am Suliman, magical advisor to his Majesty.
Ah, is that dog...?
You mean Heen?
He is a servant of mine. I had him lead you here.
I'm to understand Howl won't be joining us?
What kind of son sends his own mother
for something so important?
He'll be of no real use to you, I'm sure.
This is a problem.
Howl was my final disciple
and truly a wizard of surpassing ability.
I had planned on his becoming my successor.
Can you understand the joy I felt?
Then I find out he had sold his soul to a demon
and he flees from my scrutiny.
He resolved only to use magic
for his own gain.
Ma'am?
Yes?
Howl is dangerous.
Without a heart, he is too powerful to be left
to his own devices.
If left alone
I fear he is doomed to the same fate as the Witch of the Wastes.
Bring her in.
What did they do to you?
I've simply returned her to her true age.
Her powers have been stripped as well.
She too was once an outstanding sorceress.
By forming a pact with demons
she lost her true self over decades of solitude.
This kingdom is not in a position
to grant rogue mages license to wander freely.
Should Howl present himself here
and swear to serve the crown
I will teach him how to be free of his demonic pact.
Otherwise I will have no choice
but to strip him of his powers, as I did with her.
I must object.
I finally understand why he wouldn't dare come here.
You're odd, you people.
You make the elderly suffer up stairs.
You trick people into strange rooms like trapped animals.
You call Howl heartless?
Yes, he's a coward and a bit selfish
and I don't understand half of what he's thinking
but he is an honest man.
He just wants to be free.
Howl won't be coming here. Neither will he corrupt himself.
He'll figure out his pact
all on his own!
I know he will!
You're in love with him.
Howl? He's coming?
His heart! I want his heart!
Give it a rest, already!
Howl's not coming.
No, he will.
Now that I know his weakness.
Your Majesty.
At ease. How are you feeling?
You needn't worry.
I'm sick of all these war councils.
I needed a quick spin around the city.
What a nice day for it.
Who are they?
Howl's mother has paid us a visit.
Thank you for coming.
But I honestly don't expect to win this war through magic.
Yes, the palace is protected from the enemy's bombs
by Suliman's barriers
but then they fall on the surrounding villages instead.
Such is the nature of magic.
Am I wrong, Suliman?
You're quite the philosopher today.
It's time for the final battle!
We're going to grind them into the dust once and for all!
You've outdone yourself with this doppergänger!
Expect news of our glorious victory!
I can hardly wait.
Have the generals gathered?
They have!
Howl, it's been a long time.
I'm glad to see you well.
You didn't fool me for a moment.
I'm here, I've kept my promise.
And fighting with you is the last thing I want to do.
My mother and I will be leaving now.
No, you won't.
Don't look down. This spell is immense.
Shall I show her
what you're really like on the inside?
Howl, no, it's a trap!
Hang on!
Sophie, sit up front!
Ah... you brought them all with us.
Little doggy.
Don't look at me like that.
You're just a slave to Suliman, aren't you?
Can't exactly kick you off now, can I?
Sophie, take the controls.
I don't know how to fly this thing!
We're being followed.
I'll distract them.
You take over and fly back back to the castle.
I'll never find it!
You will. The ring will show you the way.
Picture Calcifer in your mind and see what happens.
Calcifer?
It lit up!
Just fly where it points.
You should make it by nightfall.
You should have told me you'd be coming!
It would have saved me a trip.
Knowing you were there gave me the courage.
You've seen her. How could I face her alone?
And you saved me once again.
She almost had me there.
Ah! Don't let go!
You're good at this!
You're joking!
That slowed them down a bit.
I'll give you five minutes of invisibility.
Get out of their range before it wears off.
No, I'm fine.
Thank you.
That was exciting.
I'm sure Howl thinks he's escaped me.
And what a young mother he has...
Get him!
We're almost there. That's my town down there.
I've got my eye on you.
I don't trust you after all that.
It's the castle! They came to meet us!
Markl, help!
I don't know how to stop this thing!
Doggie?
I'm home!
Sophie, are you okay?
I'm so glad.
Thanks for coming to get us.
Oh man, you've really overdone it this time.
Is he back?
Howl? Is that you?
You're in pain... are you hurt?
Get away from me.
Let me help you.
I want you free you of your curse!
...when you can't even lift your own?
I love you! I'll do whatever it takes!
You're too late.
Howl's back, isn't he.
Sophie, you need to hurry.
You need to figure out the secret of my pact with Howl!
We're almost out of time!
Or he'll turn into a demon himself?
Am I right?
I can't just tell you that!
I'm a demon, after all.
Do you know what Suliman told me?
She said that Howl
gave you something precious of his.
What is it? Where are you hiding it?
I'm really can't tell you
anything about the pact, I'm serious.
Even if I threaten you with water?
You don't know what you're saying!
That would kill Howl too.
Morning, Turnip.
I have to be brave.
Sophie, we're ready!
Okay!
Calcifer, open it wider!
Here we go!
Why... won't... you...
budge!
Seen from the inside, this "castle"
is just a patchwork of spare parts, isn't it?
Time for lunch, boys!
Here you go, granny.
Sophie, I don't like this.
That's the Witch of the Wastes.
She's harmless.
She keeps staring at me...
What a pretty flame.
Hi, guys!
Welcome back.
Howl, can we keep the dog?
Now we have a terrifying witch
and Madam Suliman's own pet dog...
Are you even trying anymore, Calcifer?
Give me a break!
Sophie just crashed her way right in here!
That must have been something to see.
Hey there. You must be Turnip.
You've got a nasty curse on you too, don't you.
We're becoming quite the odd family, aren't we?
What a handsome young man.
It's a big day today. We're moving!
We are?
Finally!
We can't even go shopping stuck up here in the mountains.
And if we stay here, Madam Suliman
will find us in no time.
You'll have to stay outside, though.
Your curse will interfere with my spells.
Alright, we're ready.
Come on over, Calcifer!
Perfect. Alright, you guys stay there.
Be gentle.
It's time.
We're done! You can come down now.
Master, it's amazing!
What a lovely flame.
This is...
I added a bathroom for you.
There are so many of us now.
Come see this. Sophie!
I put in an extra room, too.
Why this?
I thought you'd like it.
Do you?
I suppose it's perfect for a cleaning lady.
I bought you some clothes too. Take a look later.
Next!
Sophie, come here!
A courtyard!
There's a storefront too.
Heen, this way!
The door colours are different now too.
We have a few new exits.
This is my gift to you.
This is my secret garden.
It's lovely.
Did you make all this with magic?
Just a bit, to help the flowers out.
Howl, thank you!
I can hardly believe this.
It's strange. I feel like I've been here before.
I'm tearing up.
This way.
Look there.
A little hut.
It's my secret hideaway.
I spent most of my childhood summers here.
Alone?
My uncle was a wizard too
and he left this place to me.
You can come here whenever you want.
What is it?
I'm afraid.
If I go in there
I feel like I'm never going to see you again.
Howl, tell me the truth.
I don't care if you're a monster.
I just want you and the others
to be able to live in peace.
Don't you think you could open a flower shop
with everything that's growing here?
You'd do great, I know you would.
And where will you be?
Please let me help you.
I'm not... beautiful or anything.
I can't do much more than clean, but...
You are! You are beautiful!
Growing old
means you have much less to lose.
They'd even pass through these mountains?
An airship?
They're going to bomb the cities.
Is it one of ours? Or theirs?
Does it matter?
Murderers.
Look at all those bombs.
They're stopping. What did you do?
I just played with them a little. It won't crash.
Looks like they've spotted us.
The lowest of Suliman's underlings.
Time to go!
Run! Move your legs!
Head straight for the door!
Don't let go!
Sophie, what happened?
I've just about had it with you lot!
Good night, Sophie.
Good night.
Don't worry about Howl.
Sometimes he's gone for days at a time.
Thank you, Markl.
Need the bathroom?
I'm fine.
Good night, then.
You're in love.
You haven't stopped sighing
since you walked in here.
I'm right, aren't I?
Have you ever been in love?
I sure have! And I still am.
Men are a headache sometimes, but we love them anyway.
Young hearts are the best!
Not that again.
They're pretty darn cute too.
What's that?
The air raid sirens.
Here? Now?
Not us, the town over.
Still probably best to stay indoors tonight.
Suliman has her servants
wandering the town
in search of this place.
What a pretty flame. He's doing well to hide us.
Sophie, somebody weird's coming in!
Mother?
Sophie!
What happened to you?
We looked everywhere for you!
Look at you! You're so old!
It's all my fault.
I'm so sorry, Sophie.
Mother...
You've redone the whole place.
Who's that?
Ah, the head maid?
Sophie listen, I've remarried!
He's a wonderful man, and rich!
We can all live together again like we used to!
Quit being a cleaner and come home with me!
I like living like this way, it suits me.
It does?
Ah, the time!
I have a car waiting out front for me.
Sophie, I'm so glad that you're alright.
Tell me everything the next time I see you, okay?
A spy-bug?
What an old trick for Suliman to pull.
Here Cally, burn this up.
I hope you've found happiness, Mother.
I have. I wish the same for you too.
I've done as instructed.
Return me to my husband.
Of course. Madam Suliman will be quite pleased.
Forgive me, Sophie.
Look at all these people.
This place will be a ghost town
after all these people leave.
You're not joining them?
That lady offered you much the same.
She did, but... I'm just glad we could reunite.
Sophie, don't go!
Please stay. I really like you.
You're special to me too, Markl. I'm not going anywhere.
Really?
You bet.
Are we a family?
We are.
Finally!
I'll never let that Suliman get her paws on Howl.
But the paper says we already won the war.
You shouldn't believe everything you read, kid.
What's going on?
Calcifer's barely smoldering.
And will you put that out?
It reeks.
Don't deny an old bitty her fun.
Markl, can you crack open the window?
I wouldn't if I were you.
Calcifer can't protect us that well right now.
Those things will get in.
Close it!
Markl, keep an eye on granny.
I'm going to go check the store.
Now what do you want?
Help fight those fires if you've nothing better to do!
Oh my.
Forgive me. There are too many of them tonight.
Calcifer, look alive!
Madam.
These are gifts from Suliman, I take it?
She fed me something weird!
Well, if it isn't Howl.
I think we're due for a nice, long conversation, aren't we?
We are.
But you understand that now is not the time.
Not going to run away this time?
I shall return.
Sophie, stay here with the others.
Calcifer will protect you.
I'll guard the outside.
Wait!
Don't go! Stay here with me!
The next wave is coming.
Calcifer's tough but even he can't stop a bomb.
Then let's just get out of here! You don't have to fight!
Why? I've run enough.
Besides...
I've finally found someone worth protecting.
You.
That's our town!
There's Howl.
Markl, come with me.
Moving?
It'll never work, there's nowhere to warp to!
No, we have to.
Howl will keep fighting as long as we're here.
He should have stayed a coward.
Let's go. Can you stand?
Time for a walk?
Suliman will detect us right away!
She already has. Unless we do something
Howl won't be able to turn back into a person.
The castle's already falling apart!
It's fine! Here, Markl, take granny's hand.
You're coming too.
No way!
I'm forbidden from leaving the hearth!
Fine then
I'll do it for you!
Oh no, oh no!
Please, please put me back down.
The moment I pass through that door, the castle will collapse!
I don't care!
We're clear!
Our turn.
You go first, then pull me through...
I have no idea what's going to happen.
I told you this would happen.
Ah, the rain!
Is it heading for the town?
Markl, watch granny for me.
Turnip, help me find a way back in.
You'll be okay.
I'm with you.
Markl, we found a way in!
It's leaking everywhere... I'm going to go out...
Wait there.
It's wet here too!
Hurry!
It's all damp...
Markl, bring her over here.
Wow, there's nothing left.
I told you we'd be fine
if we just stayed back at the house!
Calcifer, listen to me.
You're the only one who can do this.
Take me to where Howl is.
Move the castle.
I believe in you.
There's nobody like you!
But... this place doesn't even have a chimney.
And everything's wet.
What's the old saying?
"A master doesn't complain about his tools?"
Well sure, but...
You think I can do it?
What a pretty flame.
Here's a stool for you.
In that case... why don't you give me something of yours?
Like what?
I can't do it alone... so maybe your eye? Or...
An eye?
What about this?
Calcifer, you're amazing!
I knew you could do it!
You should see what I could do with an eye or a heart!
A heart? You have a heart?
There he is! He's being surrounded.
Calcifer, hurry!
No, don't!
Granny!
Stop!
Howl's heart...!
Granny!
It's hot... so hot!
Let go of it!
You'll die!
No, it's mine!
It burns!
I'm burning!
It's mine, it's mine... I won't let anyone have it...
What have I done?
I threw water on Calcifer!
What if I've killed Howl?
It's moving. Is he alive?
Take me to him.
It's the door...
I'm in Howl's childhood!
Howl! Calcifer!
My name is Sophie! Wait for me!
One day I'll come for you, I promise!
Wait for me in the future!
I'm okay. I'm okay.
The tears just won't stop.
I'm sorry I never realized what all this was.
You were waiting for me the whole time.
Let's go home. Take me to Calcifer.
Is he dead?
He'll be alright.
It's time.
Don't look at me. I don't have it.
Please.
Please...
You really want it?
That's it then. You take care of him.
Here.
Thank you. I'll never forget this.
Sophie... I'm a wreck.
If I give Howl his heart back
will you be okay?
If you're the one to do it... it should okay.
You splashed water on me
but Howl and me were both okay, so...
I'm going to try.
What a gentle flutter.
It hasn't grown since he gave it to me.
Please... may Calcifer live a thousand years
and may Howl be himself again.
I'm alive!
I'm free!
He's alive!
Calcifer's magic wore off!
Turnip!
Turnip, are you okay?
I'll find you a new pole right away.
Turnip, thank you...
Sophie, you've done it!
I am the missing prince from the neighbouring land.
A curse had turned me into that scarecrow.
And you could only be freed
by a kiss from your beloved!
Quite right.
Had Sophie not rescued me from that bush
I would surely have died.
What a handsome young man...!
What's going on...?
My chest! Why does my chest feel so heavy?
That's what it means to have a heart.
Sophie, your hair!
It's the colour of the stars.
It's gorgeous.
Howl, I love you!
You understand her feelings, then?
I'm time for you to return home
and put a stop to this silly conflict.
And so I shall.
Once the war is over, I shall visit you again.
Do the people not say, "there are plenty of fish in the sea?"
Now that's music to my ears.
I'll be waiting.
And just where have you been?
What have you been doing?
A happy ending...
Will you be coming home, at least?
Well, that's that.
Summon the Prime Minister and the Chief of Staff.
It's time to stop this idiotic war.
Yes, ma'am.
It's Calcifer!
You didn't have to come back.
But I want to be with you guys.
Looks like it's going to rain too, so...
Thank you, Calcifer.
TRANSLATOR'S NOTES
--- The Setting ---
As with many Ghibli films,
this one is set in "fantasy Europe".
Once near the beginning
we see a war poster with German on it.
That said, the capital of this kingdom
is called "Kingsbury", an English name.
So this is likely only "Europe-inspired".
--- The War ---
In case it wasn't clear,
the disappearance of the Prince
(whose name is Justin, by the way)
was the original cause
of the war in the first place.
--- Howl and Markl ---
Mostly Markl calls Howl "Howl-san",
but just once he does refer to him
by the Japanese word "Master" (shishō).
--- The Witch of the Wastes ---
Did you notice near the end
that the Witch is shown
continuing to live with them?
Sophie is a very loving person.
She'd understand that the Witch
wouldn't be able to live on her own.
--- My Favourite Lines ---
Suliman: "I'm told you're Howl's mother."
This reflects the original Japanese
in which there's a feeling of "Apparently you're..."
indicating that Suliman doesn't buy it,
although she remains polite.
Sophie: "What have I done?"
"I threw water on Calcifer!"
"What if I've killed Howl?"
Of the possible variants,
I felt these were the most natural.
Sophie: "I'm sorry I never realized what all this was."
"You were waiting for me the whole time."
"Let's go home. Take me to Calcifer."
The three most emotional lines of the entire movie.
Thanks for watching!